<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-20T16:37:15+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>You&apos;ll find some of random thoughts let loose in here. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Learned helplessness</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2023/learned-helplessness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learned helplessness"/><published>2023-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2023/learned-helplessness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2023/learned-helplessness/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="the-curious-case-of-learned-helplessness-how-to-break-free-and-take-control">The Curious Case of Learned Helplessness: How to Break Free and Take Control</h4> <p>Imagine you’re in a maze, and every turn you take leads to a dead end. At first, you’re determined to find the way out, but after countless wrong turns, you plop down on the ground, convinced you’re stuck forever. Sounds familiar? Well, not just to maze-runners but to many of us in real life, thanks to a nifty little thing called learned helplessness. But fear not! This blog post isn’t a maze of despair; it’s your guide out of it, with a sprinkle of fun and a dash of empowerment.</p> <h4 id="a-discovery-by-accident-the-dog-days">A Discovery by Accident: The Dog Days</h4> <p>Let’s time travel to the 1960s, where psychologists Martin Seligman and Steven Maier stumbled upon learned helplessness quite by accident. Picture this: dogs in harnesses, receiving shocks they couldn’t escape. Later, when given the chance to jump away, they just lay there, having learned they were helpless. While this sounds like a downer (and, let’s be honest, not the best time to be a dog in a psychology experiment), it led to a groundbreaking understanding of why sometimes, we humans feel stuck too.</p> <h4 id="humans-not-so-different-from-our-four-legged-friends">Humans: Not So Different From Our Four-Legged Friends</h4> <p>Just like those dogs, we humans can hit a wall of helplessness after repeated setbacks. Ever felt like no matter how hard you try, you can’t ace that math test, land that dream job, or even keep a plant alive? That’s learned helplessness taking the wheel, convincing you that effort is futile. But here’s the twist: it’s not just about failing; it’s about believing we have zero control over the outcome.</p> <h4 id="spotting-learned-helplessness-in-the-wild">Spotting Learned Helplessness in the Wild</h4> <p>How do you know if you or someone you love is doing the helplessness tango? Look out for a cocktail of resignation, a dash of “why bother?” and a sprinkle of gloom. It’s like wearing defeat-colored glasses, where everything looks impossible, and the motto is “Why try if I’m going to fail anyway?”</p> <h4 id="breaking-free-the-great-escape">Breaking Free: The Great Escape</h4> <p>Now for the exciting part: how to break free from the invisible shackles of learned helplessness. It’s not just possible; it’s going to be a fun ride.</p> <ul> <li>Challenge Accepted: Transform your inner narrative from “I can’t” to “Watch me.” Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT) is like having a personal trainer for your brain, helping you flex those positivity muscles.</li> <li>Start Small, Dream Big: Conquer small tasks, then slowly raise the bar. It’s like leveling up in a video game, where each success boosts your confidence to tackle bigger bosses.</li> <li>Mindfulness: Be Here Now: Dive into meditation and mindfulness to stay present and reduce stress. Think of it as your mental spa day, every day.</li> <li>Cheer Squad: Surround yourself with a team of cheerleaders—friends, family, or a pet who believes in you blindly. Sometimes, a little nudge of encouragement is all you need to jump back into the game.</li> <li>Phone a Professional: If the going gets tough, therapists and counselors are like GPS systems guiding you out of the maze of helplessness.</li> </ul> <h4 id="the-grand-finale-taking-control">The Grand Finale: Taking Control</h4> <p>Learned helplessness might have convinced you that you’re stuck in an endless loop of “can’t,” but the truth is, you’re the captain of your ship, the master of your destiny, and yes, the hero of this maze. With the right tools and a sprinkle of determination, you can break free, take control, and rewrite your story. So, lace-up those metaphorical sneakers and get ready to take on the world—one empowered step at a time. Remember, every great adventure starts with believing you can.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a post about expanding your area of impact]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Art of Emailing a Potential PhD Research Advisor</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2019/emailing-profs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art of Emailing a Potential PhD Research Advisor"/><published>2019-03-27T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-27T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2019/emailing-profs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2019/emailing-profs/"><![CDATA[<p>Entering a PhD program is a pivotal step in your academic career, and selecting the right research advisor is crucial. Your advisor will not only influence your research direction but also shape your academic development and future opportunities. A well-crafted initial email can set the stage for a fruitful collaboration. Here’s how to reach out effectively.</p> <h4 id="start-with-a-clear-subject-line">Start with a Clear Subject Line</h4> <p>Begin with a subject line that is straightforward yet informative. It should clearly convey the purpose of your email. For example, “Interest in Your Research on [Topic]” succinctly informs the recipient of your email’s content and intent.</p> <h4 id="use-a-professional-salutation">Use a Professional Salutation</h4> <p>Address the professor formally, using “Professor [Last Name].” This shows respect and acknowledges their professional status. Even if they sign off with their first name in subsequent communications, maintain a level of formality unless invited to do otherwise.</p> <h4 id="introduce-yourself">Introduce Yourself</h4> <p>Your introduction should be brief but informative. Mention your current status (e.g., a prospective PhD student), your institution (if applicable), and how you came across their work. This contextualizes your interest and gives the professor a snapshot of who you are.</p> <h4 id="express-your-interest-clearly">Express Your Interest Clearly</h4> <p>Clearly articulate why you are interested in their research. Refer to specific papers or projects that caught your attention and briefly explain how your interests align with their work. This demonstrates that you have done your homework and are genuinely interested in their research area.</p> <h4 id="mention-your-background">Mention Your Background</h4> <p>Briefly mention relevant aspects of your academic and research background that make you a good fit for their lab. Highlight any specific skills, experiences, or accomplishments that are particularly relevant to their research.</p> <h4 id="ask-for-a-meeting-or-discussion">Ask for a Meeting or Discussion</h4> <p>Politely request the opportunity to discuss the possibility of working together. Offer flexibility in how this discussion might take place, whether through a virtual meeting, phone call, or in-person visit, depending on geographic and temporal constraints.</p> <h4 id="be-concise-and-professional">Be Concise and Professional</h4> <p>Keep your email concise and to the point. Professors are busy, and a clear, well-organized email demonstrates respect for their time. Ensure your email is free of spelling and grammatical errors and maintains a professional tone throughout.</p> <h4 id="close-politely">Close Politely</h4> <p>End your email with a courteous closing and your full name. A simple “Best regards” or “Sincerely” followed by your name suffices.</p> <h4 id="example-email-structure">Example Email Structure</h4> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Subject: Interest in Your Research on [Research Topic]

Dear Professor [Last Name],

I am [Your Name], a [Your Current Position] at [Your Institution]. I recently read your paper on [Specific Topic], and I am very interested in the work being done in your lab regarding [Research Area].

I am currently exploring PhD opportunities where I can further my interest and work on [Brief Description of Your Research Interest]. Based on my background in [Your Background] and my research experience in [Your Research Experience], I believe that I could make a significant contribution to your team.

I would be grateful if we could arrange a meeting or a phone call to discuss the possibility of working together for my PhD. I am available [provide a range of dates and times], but I am willing to adjust to your schedule.

Thank you for considering my request. I look forward to the opportunity to discuss this with you further.

Best regards,

[Your Name]
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Many thanks to Professor David Evans for writing his great <a href="https://uvasrg.github.io/prospective/">Advice for Prospective Research Students</a> that helped me with my search in the past, and inspired me to write this post.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="pain"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[series of posts about PhD journey]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating the Waters of PhD Advisor Selection</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2019/choosing-advisor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating the Waters of PhD Advisor Selection"/><published>2019-03-15T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-15T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2019/choosing-advisor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2019/choosing-advisor/"><![CDATA[<p>Embarking on a PhD is a significant milestone, filled with opportunities for growth, discovery, and personal development. Central to this experience is one crucial decision that significantly influences your journey: selecting a PhD advisor. This choice impacts not just the direction of your research but also your professional development and overall satisfaction during your PhD program.</p> <h4 id="the-person-or-the-project">The Person or the Project?</h4> <p>A piece of advice that resonates deeply within the academic community is the importance of choosing a person over a project. While it may seem crucial to continue working on a specific research topic from your undergraduate studies, the dynamics of a productive and supportive advisor-advisee relationship often outweigh the specifics of a research project. Flexibility in exploring related or even distinct fields can enrich your academic journey, highlighting the importance of the advisor’s role beyond just the research topic.</p> <h4 id="the-multidimensional-role-of-a-phd-advisor">The Multidimensional Role of a PhD Advisor</h4> <p>A PhD advisor’s role extends far beyond providing guidance on your research project. They play a pivotal role in your academic and professional development through:</p> <ul> <li><em>Technical Support:</em> Leveraging their expertise to guide your research and ensure it contributes meaningfully to your field.</li> <li><em>Academic Support:</em> Navigating academic processes, from securing funding to publishing papers, and preparing you for a successful career.</li> <li><em>Personal Support:</em> Offering mentorship and encouragement, helping you maintain well-being and motivation throughout your journey.</li> </ul> <p>In my opinion, your potential advisor should have at least 2/3. 3/3 would be a perfect chocie.</p> <h4 id="selecting-the-right-advisor">Selecting the Right Advisor</h4> <p>When selecting an advisor, consider approaching the process with an analytical mindset, focusing on collecting qualitative data through interactions with potential advisors and their current students. Key considerations include:</p> <ul> <li>Interpersonal Dynamics: Look for someone with whom you can establish a strong working relationship, valuing personal compatibility over specific research interests.</li> <li>Advisory Style and Support: Evaluate how an advisor supports their students technically, academically, and personally. Understand their approach to mentoring and how it aligns with your needs and working style.</li> <li>Flexibility and Openness to Change: Be prepared to reassess your advisor choice if your research interests evolve or if the working relationship doesn’t meet your expectations.</li> </ul> <p>This is where your investigational skills come into play. Engage with other graduate students in honest conversations to learn more about advisors. You’d be surprised how many “run away while you can” statements I heard.</p> <h4 id="the-advantage-of-a-good-match">The Advantage of a Good Match</h4> <p>A well-chosen advisor not only supports your research but also prepares you for what comes after your PhD. The right mentor can accelerate your path to independence, allowing you to pursue your career ambitions with confidence. They help you build a robust academic and professional network, opening doors to opportunities in academia, industry, or entrepreneurship.</p> <h4 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h4> <p>Choosing a PhD advisor is about finding a mentor who can guide, challenge, and support you through the rigors of graduate research. It’s about ensuring a fruitful relationship that enhances both your professional and personal growth. As you make this pivotal decision, consider not just the research you will do but the person who will accompany you on this journey, shaping your future in academia and beyond.</p> <p>Many thanks to Rob N. Candler for his eye-opening <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1502497"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Stuff most students never ask about grad school</code></a> article.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="pain"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[series of posts about PhD journey]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with code</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2015/dicegame_theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with code"/><published>2015-07-15T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-07-15T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2015/dicegame_theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2015/dicegame_theory/"><![CDATA[<p>So this is a dice game with some interesting game theory involved. I was a little surprised to find most solutions online seemed incorrect to me so I solved it to find out.</p> <p>Solutions posted online are the following:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">text
</span>
the expected value for the roll is 15.5 so to maximize winning player A can immedietly get one of the closest positions to minimize distance. 16 is the better of the two 15 and 16

<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>That can’t be true! Can it? Let’s find out!</p> <p>To find out if it’s better to be player A or B, we need to find out what are the expected winnings for each player VS the other. There are three things we need to find out:</p> <ol> <li>What is the optimal policy for B given A’s choice?</li> <li>What is the optimal policy for A given B’s choice?</li> </ol> <p>I think the first part is easier. For a given choice of A, what’s the best policy? When A chooses a value, they effectively split the problem into two dice games, and B’s choice is to pick which dice they want to be rewarded. If A picks 15, the expected value of winnings &gt; 15 is naturally higher than those of &lt; 15. Whatever B choses, A, automatically wins all the rolls on the opposite side, plus they share what’s in between them and B. Naturally, to limit A’s winnings, picking the roll immedietly adjacent to to their choice, minimizes their winnings for that choice. So the optimal policy for B is either A+1 or A-1, depending on which side has higher expected value.</p> <p>Now that we’ve identified B’s optimal choice, next, is finding what’s the optimal choice for A. It’s a straight forward search problem, and the solution space is small so no issues there. Let’s set the problem up.</p> <p>To calculate the expected winnings for both players, let’s create function <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">calculate_expected_winnings</code>:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># Function to calculate expected winnings for Player A and Player B
</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">calculate_expected_winnings</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">expected_winnings_A</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
    <span class="n">expected_winnings_B</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
    
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">n_A</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n_sides</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="n">winnings_A</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
        <span class="n">winnings_B</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
              
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">n_A</span> <span class="o">&lt;=</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="c1"># Compare the expected utility of choosing n_A - 1 vs n_A + 1 for B
</span>            <span class="c1"># This simplification assumes equal probability for all rolls and does not account for the exact expected utility calculation
</span>            <span class="n">optimal_B_policy</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">n_A</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
        <span class="k">elif</span> <span class="n">n_A</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">optimal_B_policy</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">n_A</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
        
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">roll</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n_sides</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="c1"># Determine winner based on roll
</span>            <span class="n">distance_A</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">abs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">roll</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">n_A</span><span class="p">)</span>
            <span class="n">distance_B</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">abs</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">roll</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">optimal_B_policy</span><span class="p">)</span>
            
            <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">distance_A</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">distance_B</span><span class="p">:</span>
                <span class="n">winnings_A</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">roll</span>
            <span class="k">elif</span> <span class="n">distance_B</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">distance_A</span><span class="p">:</span>
                <span class="n">winnings_B</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">roll</span>
            <span class="c1"># In case of a tie, split the winnings (though ties are very unlikely in this setup)
</span>            <span class="k">else</span><span class="p">:</span>
                <span class="n">winnings_A</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">roll</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">2</span>
                <span class="n">winnings_B</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">roll</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">2</span>
        
        <span class="c1"># Calculate expected winnings
</span>        <span class="n">expected_winnings_A</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">winnings_A</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">n_sides</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="n">expected_winnings_B</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">append</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">winnings_B</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">n_sides</span><span class="p">)</span>
    
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">expected_winnings_A</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">expected_winnings_B</span>

</code></pre></div></div> <p>Now we search and generate the plot:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># Search for the optimal choice
</span><span class="n">total_expected_winnings_by_x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="nf">calculate_total_expected_winnings_for_B</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">n_sides</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)]</span>

<span class="c1"># Find the x with the highest total expected winnings for Player B
</span><span class="n">optimal_x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">total_expected_winnings_by_x</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">index</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">max</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">total_expected_winnings_by_x</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span>

<span class="c1"># Calculate the expected winnings for Player A and Player B at the optimal x
</span><span class="n">expected_winnings_A</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">expected_winnings_B</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">calculate_expected_winnings</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">optimal_x</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Plotting the results:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/overall_winnings.svg-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/overall_winnings.svg-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/overall_winnings.svg-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/overall_winnings.svg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/winnings_closer-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/winnings_closer-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/winnings_closer-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/winnings_closer.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Ok so knowing what we know, in absolute terms, player A can have the highest expected return when choosing 21. But I wouldn’t want to be player A for that small of an edge, with that huge downside (significantly less winnings for the rest of choice). I would take B as in the worst case scenario, I am better positioned to win “almost” as much as A, if they play perfectly. Otherwise, I have much higher upside.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="puzzle"/><category term="probability"/><category term="probability"/><category term="puzzle"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with some code]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with TikZJax</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2011/tikzjax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with TikZJax"/><published>2011-12-12T22:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-12-12T22:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2011/tikzjax</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2011/tikzjax/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with TikZ code. TikZJax converts script tags (containing TikZ code) into SVGs.</p> <script type="text/tikz">
\begin{tikzpicture}
    \draw[red,fill=black!60!red] (0,0) circle [radius=1.5];
    \draw[green,fill=black!60!green] (0,0) circle [x radius=1.5cm, y radius=10mm];
    \draw[blue,fill=black!60!blue] (0,0) circle [x radius=1cm, y radius=5mm, rotate=30];
\end{tikzpicture}

</script> <p>below is another</p> <script type="text/tikz">

\begin{tikzpicture}
  \path[mindmap,concept color=black,text=white]
    node[concept] {Computer Science}
    [clockwise from=0]
    child[concept color=green!50!black] {
      node[concept] {practical}
      [clockwise from=90]
      child { node[concept] {algorithms} }
      child { node[concept] {data structures} }
      child { node[concept] {pro\-gramming languages} }
      child { node[concept] {software engineer\-ing} }
    }  
    child[concept color=blue] {
      node[concept] {applied}
      [clockwise from=-30]
      child { node[concept] {databases} }
      child { node[concept] {WWW} }
    }
    child[concept color=red] { node[concept] {technical} }
    child[concept color=orange] { node[concept] {theoretical} };
\end{tikzpicture}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included TikZ code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with TikZJax</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2000/tikzjax-copy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with TikZJax"/><published>2000-12-12T02:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2000-12-12T02:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2000/tikzjax%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2000/tikzjax-copy/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with TikZ code. TikZJax converts script tags (containing TikZ code) into SVGs.</p> <script type="text/tikz">

\begin{tikzpicture}
  \path[mindmap,concept color=black,text=white]
    node[concept] {Computer Science}
    [clockwise from=0]
    child[concept color=green!50!black] {
      node[concept] {practical}
      [clockwise from=90]
      child { node[concept] {algorithms} }
      child { node[concept] {data structures} }
      child { node[concept] {pro\-gramming languages} }
      child { node[concept] {software engineer\-ing} }
    }  
    child[concept color=blue] {
      node[concept] {applied}
      [clockwise from=-30]
      child { node[concept] {databases} }
      child { node[concept] {WWW} }
    }
    child[concept color=red] { node[concept] {technical} }
    child[concept color=orange] { node[concept] {theoretical} };
\end{tikzpicture}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included TikZ code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with jupyter notebook</title><link href="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2000/jupyter-notebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with jupyter notebook"/><published>2000-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2000-07-04T12:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2000/jupyter-notebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abdulalkurdi.com/blog/2000/jupyter-notebook/"><![CDATA[<p>To include a jupyter notebook in a post, you can use the following code:</p> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>{::nomarkdown}
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">relative_url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">capture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">file_exists</span><span class="w"> </span>assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb<span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endcapture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'true'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  <span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">jupyter_notebook</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  &lt;p&gt;Sorry, the notebook you are looking for does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
{:/nomarkdown}
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Let’s break it down: this is possible thanks to <a href="https://github.com/red-data-tools/jekyll-jupyter-notebook">Jekyll Jupyter Notebook plugin</a> that allows you to embed jupyter notebooks in your posts. It basically calls <a href="https://nbconvert.readthedocs.io/en/latest/usage.html#convert-html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jupyter nbconvert --to html</code></a> to convert the notebook to an html page and then includes it in the post. Since <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/configuration/markdown/">Kramdown</a> is the default Markdown renderer for Jekyll, we need to surround the call to the plugin with the <a href="https://kramdown.gettalong.org/syntax.html#extensions">::nomarkdown</a> tag so that it stops processing this part with Kramdown and outputs the content as-is.</p> <p>The plugin takes as input the path to the notebook, but it assumes the file exists. If you want to check if the file exists before calling the plugin, you can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">file_exists</code> filter. This avoids getting a 404 error from the plugin and ending up displaying the main page inside of it instead. If the file does not exist, you can output a message to the user. The code displayed above outputs the following:</p> <div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/blog.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div> <p>Note that the jupyter notebook supports both light and dark themes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="jupyter"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with jupyter notebook]]></summary></entry></feed>